<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" ?>
<document>
  <properties>
    <title>Goals</title>
  </properties>

  <meta name="keyword" content="java, junit"/>

  <body>
    <section name="Project goals">
      <subsection name="Ease the testing of Swing-based GUIs">
        <p>UISpec4j's main goal is to provide a support for writing unit and functional
          test cases based on the application's user interface.</p>
        <p>UISpec4J was conceived in an Extreme Programming environment, where automated testing takes
           a central place. The existing Swing-based testing frameworks did expose too much of
           the Swing APIs, resulting in arcane and unmaintainable scripts.
           This is why we decided to implement a set of wrappers, trying to make our
           test scripts as close as possible to human-readable text.</p>
      </subsection>

      <subsection name="Provide a code-oriented tool">
        <p>Some GUI testing tools capture low-level Swing events, allowing testers to
           manually record sequences of user interactions with the user interface. This makes tests
           scenarios quite easy to create, but on a moderately large application the maintenance of these
           scenarios can become a nightmare, discouraging the team from making any change in the
           user interface.</p>
        <p>We believe that the functional tests suite of an application must be <i>designed</i> as
           any significant piece of code: variables, methods, classes, everything a programming language
           might offer must be used to create a readable, maintainable whole.</p>
        <p>By making UISpec4J available as a Java library, we can let its users benefit from the
           features of the Java language and platform. This makes it also available for writing unit
           tests for GUI classes based on Swing. <br/>
           Users wanting a script-like interface can also simply wrap our library using tools such as
           <a href="http://groovy.codehaus.org/">Groovy</a> or
           <a href="http://www.beanshell.org/">BeanShell</a>.</p>
      </subsection>

      <subsection name="Promote the use of functional testing as advocated by XP">
        <p>In the Extreme Programming process, functional test cases <i>are</i> the detailed
          specifications of the product. This is what UI<b><i>Spec</i></b>4J is made for:
          providing a language as simple as possible for writing these specifications.</p>
      </subsection>
    </section>
  </body>
</document>